<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>multivac61.github.com</title>
    <link>multivac61.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on multivac61.github.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="multivac61.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Intro to modern hardware prototyping</title>
      <link>multivac61.github.io/modern_hardware_prototyping/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>multivac61.github.io/modern_hardware_prototyping/</guid>
      <description>This post is a brief overview of hardware (HW) prototyping. It is meant for individuals or teams that are starting their journey into the magical forest of HW prototyping. The topic is huge and it is impossible to cover all aspects of it in a blog post. Your situation, needs and requirements will also be different from ours. This is the post I wish I had read two years ago before I finished my undergrad degree in electrical engineering.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digitizing analog circuits containing op amps using Wave Digital Filters</title>
      <link>multivac61.github.io/emulating-op-amp-circuits-using-wdf-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>multivac61.github.io/emulating-op-amp-circuits-using-wdf-theory/</guid>
      <description>In this post I will share some work I have been doing on Wave Digital Filters, or WDFs for short. WDFs allows one to digitize analog reference circuits in a way that retains the underlying topology, has nice numerical properties, allows for breaking up of annoying delay-free loops when digitizing and has a very nice modular way of dealing with non-linearities. I will not explain the basic WDF theory here but if you are interested the omnipotent paper on the subject written by Fettweis, the creator of WDF, or this tutorial on WDF should get you familiar with the topic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental frequency estimation and supervised learning</title>
      <link>multivac61.github.io/fundamental-frequency-estimation-and-machine-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>multivac61.github.io/fundamental-frequency-estimation-and-machine-learning/</guid>
      <description>This post is a report on a final project I did in a music technology graduate seminar, MUMT-605, offered at McGill in the fall of 2015.
Fundamental frequency estimation Fundamental frequency (f0) estimation (sometimes also called pitch detection, see Appendix A) has been an active topic of research within the field of audio signal processing for many years. Currently there exist literally hundreds of estimation methods that most do fairly well when the sound source is monophonic and noiseless but tend to differ greatly in accuracy when applied in less ideal situations [1, 4].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Knight&#39;s Tour</title>
      <link>multivac61.github.io/knights_tour/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>multivac61.github.io/knights_tour/</guid>
      <description>Another interesting problem relating to classical search in AI is the Knight&amp;rsquo;s Tour.
A knight&amp;rsquo;s tour is a sequence of moves of a knight on a chessboard such that the knight visits every square only once. If the knight ends on a square that is one knight&amp;rsquo;s move from the beginning square (so that it could tour the board again immediately, following the same path), the tour is closed, otherwise it is open.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The problem with N queens</title>
      <link>multivac61.github.io/n_queens_problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>multivac61.github.io/n_queens_problem/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m currently taking an introductory course in AI at McGill. In reality the course is not really an introductory course as it covers a broad range of theory and is extremely demanding (as in bloody hard). That being said I feel like I&amp;rsquo;m getting a good overview of the general landscape of AI, which is awesome.
The course textbook we&amp;rsquo;re using is AI: A Modern Approach. In a chapter about classical search the authors talk about a problem called the 8-Queens problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Note to self.self: List comprehensions in Python 2.x leak!</title>
      <link>multivac61.github.io/note-to-self/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>multivac61.github.io/note-to-self/</guid>
      <description>After considerable amount of debugging on some code I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing in Python 2.x I finally found the bug. This time it didn&amp;rsquo;t arise because I was sloppy, as it so often does, but because of faulty behaviour intrinsic to the language design of Python 2.x itself..
  &amp;#39;This is an example of list comprehension control variables being leaked to their outer scope&amp;#39; for i in range(10): a = [i for i in range(43)] print(i) # will print 42 every time!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sorting algorithms in Python</title>
      <link>multivac61.github.io/sorting_algorithms_in_python/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>multivac61.github.io/sorting_algorithms_in_python/</guid>
      <description>Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing some coding in Python but I felt like I didn&amp;rsquo;t really understand what was going on. So as a way to better understand python&amp;rsquo;s syntax and semantics I implemented a couple of the better known sorting algorithms - for fun and the greater good!
This post showcases the code I wrote and talks about the hurdles I encountered while implementing the algorithms. This post is only meant to document my learning process of Python implementations and not really meant for learning about the mathematics behind the space- and time complexities of the different sort algorithms as I had already done that in my EE undergrad.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>multivac61.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>multivac61.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>This Theme Thanks for visiting this theme demo. If you&amp;rsquo;re interested, checkout my other stuff over at https://zwbetz.com
Hugo Hugo is the world’s fastest framework for building websites. It is written in Go.
It makes use of a variety of open source projects including:
 https://github.com/russross/blackfriday https://github.com/alecthomas/chroma https://github.com/muesli/smartcrop https://github.com/spf13/cobra https://github.com/spf13/viper  Learn more and contribute on GitHub.
 Favicon made by Freepik, from Flaticon, licensed by CC 3.0.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>